I've got a confession.
عندي إعتراف.
I love looking through people's garbage.
أحبُ البحث بين قمامة الناس.
Now, it's not some creepy thing.
حالياً، إنها ليست شيء مقزز.
I'm usually just looking for old electronics,
إنني عادةً أبحثُ عن الإلكترونيات القديمة فقط
stuff I can take to my workshop and hack.
أشياء يمكنُ لي أن آخذها لورشة عملي وأفكها.
I do have a fetish for CD-ROM drives.
لديّ عشق للأقراص المغضوطة المدمجة.
Each one's got three different motors,
لدى كل واحد ثلاثة محركات مختلفة،
so now you can build things that move.
لذلك تستطيعون الآن بناء أشياء تتحرك.
There's switches so you can turn things on and off.
هناك مفاتيح كهربائية تستطيعون بها إشعال أو إطفاء الأشياء.
There's even a freaking laser,
ويوجد أيضا ليزر بألوان متنوعة،
so you can make a cool robot into an awesome robot.
حيثُ يمكنكم جعل إنسان آلي هادىء إلى إنسان آلي مذهل.
Now, I've built a lot of stuff out of garbage,
بنيتُ حالياً الكثير من الأشياء من القمامة،
and some of these things have even been kind of useful.
حتى حتى أن بعضها كان مفيدا نوعاً ما.
But here's the thing,
لكن إليكم هذا الشيء،
for me, garbage is just a chance to play,
القمامة بالنسبة لي هي مجرد فرصة للعب،
to be creative and build things to amuse myself.
لأكون مبدعاً وأبني أشياء تروق لي وتسليني.
This is what I love doing, so I just made it part of my day job.
هذا هو ما أحب القيام به، لذلك جعلته جزء من عملي اليومي.
I lead a university-based biological research lab,
أقودُ مختبراً جامعياً معتمداً على بحوث علم الأحياء،
where we value curiosity and exploration above all else.
حيثُ نقدرُ الفضول والإكتشافات قبل كل شيء.
We aren't focused on any particular problem,
نحنُ لا نركزُ على أية مشكلة محددة،
and we're not trying to solve any particular disease.
ولا نحاولُ حل أي مرض معين.
This is just a place where people can come
إنه مجرد مكان حيثُ يمكن للناس الحضور
and ask fascinating questions and find answers.
وطرح الأسئلة المهمة والعثور على الأجوبة.
And I realized a long time ago
وأدركتُ قبل فترة طويلة
that if I challenge people to build the equipment they need
أنني إذا تحديتُ الناس لبناء أجهزة يحتاجونها
out of the garbage I find,
من القمامة التي أجدها،
it's a great way to foster creativity.
فهذه هي وسيلة رائعة لتعزيز الإبداع.
And what happened
وما حدث هو
was that artists and scientists from around the world
أن الفنانين والعلماء من جميع أنحاء العالم
started coming to my lab.
قد بدأوا في الحضور إلى مختبري.
And it's not just because we value unconventional ideas,
وهذا ليس بسبب أننا نقدرُ الأفكار الغريبة فقط.
it's because we test and validate them
بل لأننا نختبرُ ونتأكدُ من صحتها
with scientific rigor.
بدقة علمية.
So one day I was hacking something, I was taking it apart,
كنتُ ذات يوم أفكك شيئاً، كنتُ أفصله إلى أجزاء،
and I had this sudden idea:
وخطرت لي هذه الفكرة الفجائية:
Could I treat biology like hardware?
هل بإمكاني التعامل مع الأحياء مثل العناصر المادية التي تشكل نظام الحاسوب؟
Could I dismantle a biological system,
هل بإمكاني تفكيك النظام البيولوجي الحي،
mix and match the parts
مزج وتنسيق ووصل الأجزاء
and then put it back together in some new and creative way?
ومن ثم وضعها معاً مرة أخرى في طريقة خلاّقة جديدة نوعاً ما؟
My lab started working on this,
بداً مختبري العمل على ذلك،
and I want to show you the result.
وأودُ أن أطلعكم على النتيجة.
Can any of you guys tell me what fruit this is?
هل يمكن لأي أحد منكم أن يقول لي ما نوع هذه الفاكهة ؟
Audience: Apple!
الجمهور: تفاحة!
Andrew Pelling: That's right -- it's an apple.
أندرو بيلنغ: هذا صحيح-- إنها تفاحة.
Now, I actually want you to notice as well
في الحقيقة، أريدُ منكم الآن أن تلاحظوا
that this is a lot redder than most apples.
أن هذه هي أكثر إحمراراً من معظم التفاح.
And that's because we grew human cells into it.
وهذا بسبب أننا زرعنا خلايا بشرية فيها.
We took a totally innocent Macintosh apple,
أخذنا تفاحة جهاز ماكنتوش خالية من العطب،
removed all the apple cells and DNA
وأزلنا كل خلايا التفاحة والحمض النووي
and then implanted human cells.
ومن ثم زرعنا خلايا بشرية.
And what we're left with after removing all the apple cells
وما تبقى لدينا بعد إزالة كل خلايا التفاحة
is this cellulose scaffold.
هو هذه السقالة السليلوزية.
This is the stuff that gives plants their shape and texture.
هذا هو الشيء الذي يعطي المزروعات شكلها وملمسها.
And these little holes that you can see,
وهذه الثقوب الصغيرة التي ترونها،
this is where all the apple cells used to be.
هي حيث خلايا التفاحة إعتادت أن تكون.
So then we come along,
و بعد ذلك مباشرة،
we implant some mammalian cells that you can see in blue.
زرعنا بعضاً من خلايا الثدييات التي يمكنكم رؤيتها باللون الأزرق.
What happens is, these guys start multiplying
ما حدثُ هو أن هذه الأجسام بدأت بالتكاثر
and they fill up this entire scaffold.
وملأت هذه السقالة بالكامل.
As weird as this is,
على الرغم من أن هذا الأمر يبدو غريبا،
it's actually really reminiscent of how our own tissues are organized.
فهي في الحقيقة تذكرنا بكيفية تنظيم أنسجتنا.
And we found in our pre-clinical work
ووجدنا في عمل ما قبل السريرية خاصتنا
that you can implant these scaffolds into the body,
أنه يمكن زراعة هذه السقالات في الجسم،
and the body will send in cells and a blood supply
وسيرسل الجسم الخلايا وإمدادات الدم
and actually keep these things alive.
وستبقى هذه الأشياء على قيد الحياة فعلاً.
This is the point when people started asking me,
عند هذه النقطة، بدأ الناس يطلبون مني،
"Andrew, can you make body parts out of apples?"
"أندرو، هل يمكنك عمل أجزاء الجسم من التفاحة؟"
And I'm like, "You've come to the right place."
فأجيب : "لقد أتيتم إلى المكان الصحيح."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I actually brought this up with my wife.
لقد أثرتُ هذه المسألة في الحقيقة مع زوجتي.
She's a musical instrument maker,
إنها صانعة آلات موسيقية،
and she does a lot of wood carving for a living.
وتقوم بالكثير من النقش على الخشب
So I asked her,
لذلك سألتها :
"Could you, like, literally carve some ears
"هل يمكنكي ،حَرْفيا، نحت بعض الآذان
out of an apple for us?"
انطلاقا من تفاحة من أجلنا؟"
And she did.
وقامت بعمل ذلك.
So I took her ears to the lab.
لذا، أخذتُ الآذان التي صنعتها إلى المختبر.
We then started preparing them.
وثم بدأنا في تحضيرها.
Yeah, I know.
نعم، إنني أعلمُ.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's a good lab, man.
إنه مختبر جيد، إنه مثيرٌ للحماس.
And then we grew cells on them.
ثم زرعنا فيهم خلايا .
And this is the result.
وهذه هي النتيجة.
Listen, my lab is not in the ear-manufacturing business.
إنتبهوا، مختبري لا ينتمي إلى مجال تصينع الآذان.
People have actually been working on this for decades.
يعمل الناس في الحقيقة على هذا منذ عقودٍ من الزمن.
Here's the issue:
وهنا المشكلة:
commercial scaffolds can be really expensive and problematic,
يمكنُ للسقالات التجارية أن تكون حقاً غالية الثمن وشائكة.
because they're sourced from proprietary products,
لأن مصدرها هو المنتوجات ذات الملكية الخاصة،
animals or cadavers.
والحيوانات أو الجثث.
We used an apple and it cost pennies.
إستخدمنا تفاحة، وكلفت بنسات.
What's also really cool here
ما هو مُطمئِن هنا حقاً
is it's not that hard to make these things.
هوأن صنع هذه الأشياء ليس بالأمر الصعب
The equipment you need can be built from garbage,
يمكنكم بناء ما تحتاجونه من معدات باستخدام القمامة،
and the key processing step only requires soap and water.
وتتطلب مرحلة المعالجة الأساسية الماء والصابون فقط.
So what we did was put all the instructions online as open source.
ما قمنا به هو وضع كل التعليمات على شبكة الإنترنت كمصدر مفتوح.
And then we founded a mission-driven company,
ثم عثرنا على شركة تحركها المهمة،
and we're developing kits to make it easier
ونحن نعملُ على تطوير معدات لجعل الأمر أكثر سهولة
for anyone with a sink and a soldering iron
لأي شخص لديه حوض وسبيكة لحام
to make these things at home.
لصنع هذه الأشياء في المنزل.
What I'm really curious about is if one day,
ما يهمني حقاً هو هل يمكن في يوم من الأيام
it will be possible to repair, rebuild and augment our own bodies
إصلاح وإعادة بناء وزراعة أجسامنا الخاصة
with stuff we make in the kitchen.
بأشياء نعملها في المطبخ.
Speaking of kitchens,
بمناسبة الحديث عن المطابخ،
here's some asparagus.
إليكم بعضا من نبات الهليون.
They're tasty, and they make your pee smell funny.
إنها لذيذة الطعم، وتجعل رائحة البول عندكم غريبة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now, I was in my kitchen, and I was noticing
كنتُ في مطبخي ولاحظتُ
that when you look down the stalks of these asparagus,
أنه وعندما تنظرون أسفل سيقان الهليون،
what you can see are all these tiny little vessels.
ما يمكنكم رؤيته هو هذه الأوعية متناهية الصغر.
And when we image them in the lab,
وعندما عكسنا صورتها في المختبر،
you can see how the cellulose forms these structures.
تمكنا من رؤية كيف يُشكلُ السليولوز هذه التركيبات،
This image reminds me of two things:
تذكرني هذه الصورة بأمرين:
our blood vessels
أوعيتنا الدموعة
and the structure and organization of our nerves and spinal cord.
وتركيبة وتنظيم الأعصاب والحبل الشوكي لدينا
So here's the question:
لذا فالسؤال هو:
Can we grow axons and neurons down these channels?
هل يمكننا زرغ محاور وخلايا عصبية أسفل هذه القنوات؟
Because if we can,
لأنه إذا إستطعنا ذلك،
then maybe we can use asparagus to form new connections
فعندها ربما يمكننا إستخدام نبات الهليون لتشكيل وصلات جديدة
between the ends of damaged and severed nerves.
بين طرفي الأعصاب التالفة والمقطوعة.
Or maybe even a spinal cord.
أو ربما حتى الحبل الشوكي.
Don't get me wrong --
لا تسيؤوا فهمي،
this is exceptionally challenging
إنه تحدي إستثنائي
and really hard work to do,
وعمل جاد حقاً ،
and we are not the only ones working on this.
و لسنا نحن فقط من يعمل على ذلك.
But we are the only ones using asparagus.
ولكن نحنُ وحدنا من يستخدم الهليون.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Right now, we've got really promising pilot data.
لدينا حالياً بيانات تجريبية واعدة حقاً.
And we're working with tissue engineers
ونحنُ نعملُ مع مهندسي الأنسجة الحيوية
and neurosurgeons
وجرَّاحي الأعصاب
to find out what's actually possible.
لمعرفة ما يمكننا فعلا القيام به.
So listen, all of the work I've shown you,
إنتبهوا، كل العمل الذي أريتكم إياه،
the stuff that I've built that's all around me on this stage
الأشياء التي بنيتها والتي تُوجَد حولي فوق هذه الخشبة
and the other projects my lab is involved in
والمشاريع الأخرى التي يعمل عليها مختبري
are all a direct result of me playing with your garbage.
جميعها نتيجة مباشرة للعبي بقمامتكم.
Play -- play is a key part of my scientific practice.
اللعب-- اللعب هو جزء أساسي من تجاربي العلمية.
It's how I train my mind to be unconventional and to be creative
إني أدربُ ذهني بواسطته كي يكون غير تقليدي ومبدع
and to decide to make human apple ears.
وكيف يُقرر صُنع آذان بشرية من التفاح.
So, the next time any of you are looking at some old,
لذلك، إذا كان أحدكم يوما ما ينظر لشيء قديم
broken-down, malfunctioning, piece-of-crap technology,
لقطعة خردة تكنولوجية مكسورة ومعطوبة،
I want you to think of me.
أريدكم أن تفكروا بي.
Because I want it.
لأنني أريدها.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Seriously, please find any way to get in touch with me,
أنا جاد، من فضلكم أعثروا على أية طريقة للإتصال بي،
and let's see what we can build.
ودعونا نرى ما يمكن بناؤه.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)